Finding Aid for Sid Gilman papers, 1961-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sid Gilman papers 1961-2003
Gilman, Sid, 1932-
0556 Aa 2
The Sid Gilman collection consists of biographical, UM departmental, research, and grant information, in addition to numerous lectures and presentations that Gilman has given during his tenure at both Columbia University and the University of Michigan. Correspondence, filmstrips, photographs, videotape, and other media are distributed throughout the collection. Material about Derek Denny-Brown is also included.
9 linear feet
1 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated in March and December of 2004 (Donor no. 9466 )
The record group is open without restriction with the exception of one folder restricted and removed.
Sid Gilman served as professor and chair of the University of Michigan Department of Neurology from 1977 to 2003 and was inaugurated as the first William J. Herdman Professor of Neurology in 1997. He received his undergraduate and medical degrees from the University of California at Los Angeles, graduating with the M.D. in 1957. After serving a year-long internship at the UCLA hospital, Gilman served as Research Associate at the National Institutes of Health for two years, then as Resident in Neurology at Harvard Medical School/Boston City Hospital Neurological Unit for three years. For the next two years, he was a research fellow, then a faculty member (first as an instructor, then as an associate) at Harvard Medical School/Boston City Hospital. In 1968, he left Harvard for Columbia University, where he joined as an Assistant Professor before becoming an Associate Professor, then Professor. He became the H. Houston Merit Professor of Neurology in 1976. The following year, he left Columbia for the University of Michigan.
Dr. Gilman received numerous awards and honors during his career. In addition to being a member of Phi Beta Kappa and Alpha Omega Alpha, he was the recipient of the Lucy G. Moses Prize in Basic Neurology, the UCLA Alumni Professional Achievement Award, and the UCLA Medical Alumni Professional Achievement Award. He belonged to several organizations, including the American Neurological Association and the Michigan Neurological Association, and served as President of both organizations. He is the author of over 300 journal articles and book chapters and wrote and edited six books. In addition, he served as Editor-in-Chief of the Contemporary Neurology Series, MedLink Neurology, and Experimental Neurology. He was a member of the editorial board of six other neurological journals. His work concerns neurodegenerative diseases, including Parkinson's and Alzheimer's, and cerebellar degenerations, modern approaches to imaging the nervous system, and the neurophysiological and neuropharmacological aspects of cerebellar and basal ganglia function.
The Sid Gilman collection consists primarily of correspondence and research papers detailing his professional career, although photographs, filmstrips, slides, and other images are also distributed throughout the collection. This collection is divided into seven series: Biographical Info, Professional Info, UM Neurology Department Info, Decade of the Brain, Lectures/Presentations, Denny-Brown Material and, Research. Two of these series are further divided into two sub-series. Parts of the collection are arranged in alphabetical order for ease of use, although the remaining series have been maintained in their original order. In addition, some of the contents are partially arranged in reverse chronological order, also as maintained originally.
Subjects:
Gilman, Sid, 1932-; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Dept. of Neurology.
- Biographical
  Biographical Info (0.5 feet) contains tributes, honors, and awards that Gilman received throughout his career as a faculty member of the UM Neurology department. Notable honors include the Henry Russel award, and a tribute given in 2003. A videotape of the tribute is also included.
  - Tribute (videotape) 2003 (Box 1)
  - "Best Doctors" Nominations 2002-2003 (Box 1)
  - 2001 Henry Russel Lecture, 1999-2001 (contains films) (Box 1)
  - News Articles (quotes) 1978, 1984, 1987, 1991, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
  - Portrait Correspondence 1994-1995, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
  - Honors/Awards 1987-1988, 1990-1991, 1993-1996, 1998 (Box 1)
  - UCLA Professional Achievement Award 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Biographies/Profiles 1991, 1992, 1994, 1996 (Box 1)
- Professional
  The Professional Info series (approx. 1 box total) consists of correspondence between Gilman and members of the various organizations and committees of which he was a part. There may also be some correspondence between members other than Gilman. The bulk of the files relate to the American Neurological association (ANA), but other organizations include the American Medical Association, the American Academy of Neurology (AAN), and the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS). The material in the Decade of the Brain series is related to Professional Info in that there is much correspondence between members of the AAN.
  - AAN/ANA Archives 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - ABPN/ANA/AAN Correspondence 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - American Board of Clinical Neurophysiology (ABCN) 1988 (Box 1)
  - American Neurological Association (ANA)
    - Administration 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - ANA/Council of Academic Societies (CAS; part of Association of American Medical Colleges) 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - Annual Meeting 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Bylaws, Financial Statements, Presidential Symposium 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Calendar 1988 (Box 1)
    - Carotid Endarterectomy 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Ethical Issues 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Committees (General Info) 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Constitution and Bylaws 1983, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Executive Council 1985-1986, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Health Care Issues Committee, ANA Council 1986 (Box 1)
    - History of the Association Committee 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - Long Range Planning Committee 1976-1980, 1983-1984, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
  - ANA/AMA (American Medical Association) 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Annals of Neurology
    - Oversight Committee 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - Little, Brown, and Company 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Finance Committee 1987-1989 (Box 1)
  - Geriatrics Section Education Subcommittee 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Honorary Membership Advisory Committee 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Interagency Head Injury Task Force 1988 (Box 1)
  - Intersociety Committee on Neurological Resources (ICNR) 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Jacoby Award 1989 (Box 1)
  - Membership Advisory Committee 1979, 1981, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Parkinson's Initiative (MPI) (date unknown) (Box 1)
  - Motor Control 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - National Coalition for Research 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Ortho/McNeil (Neuroscience Advisory Board) 1997-1999 (Box 1)
  - Misc. 1995-1998, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - NANDS/NINDS 1994-1995 (Box 2)
  - National Advisory Council and Board Representatives Meeting 1996 (Box 2)
  - National Advisory of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NANDS), Financial Disclosure 1996-1997 (Box 2)
  - Parkinson's Disease 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - Peripheral and Central Nervous System Drugs Advisory Committee
    - 1986, 1992-1997 (Box 2)
    - 1997-2000 (Box 2)
    - Office of Government Ethics and Financial Disclosure Reports 1994, 1996-1999 (Box 2)
    - Peck Letter 1993 (Box 2)
  - Therapy in Neurology 1989 (Box 2)
- University of Michigan Department of Neurology
  The UM Departmental series (approx. 1 1/2 boxes) is divided into two sub-series. The Neurology Department info sub-series contains the history of and information about the department. There are also internal and external departmental reviews, annual reports, meeting minutes, and committee information. In addition, there are also several photographs of faculty members and residents. The bulk of the Grant Info sub-series consists of grant applications and Markey Grant annual progress reports (the Markey Grant being awarded through the Markey Charitable Trust, a limited term trust which was established to fund research grants to scientists, M.D.s, and Ph.Ds in the field of biomedical research).
  - Grants
    - Grant Proposal, Disorders of Cerebral Biochemistry and Alcoholism 1998 (Box 2)
    - Markey Charitable Trust: Markey Grant Annual Progress Reports 1989-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Neurobase Info 1991, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Summary Statement and Grant Application 1996-1997 (Box 2)
    - Training in Clinical and Basic Neuroscience (grant application) 2001, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Topical Files
    - Alcohol Research Center Grant (PET) 1988, 1991, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - DeJong Society papers 1983-1998 (Box 3)
    - Dept. of Neurology Long Range Planning Committee 1985-1987 (Box 3)
    - External and Internal Reviews/Annual Reports 1977-2002 (Box 3)
    - External and Internal Reviews (folder 1) 1986-1994 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Curriculum Vitae, Bios, and Obituaries 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - Annual Reports (folder 2) 1986-1995 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Photos (large envelope) 1938-2003 (some years missing) (Box 3)
    - Faculty photos (small envelopes), (dates unknown) (Box 3)
    - Internal Reviews 1984-1997, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Minutes, Resident Education Committee 1983-1987, 1990-1994 (Box 3)
    - Misc 1966, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Misc. Dept. Info 1987-1999 (Box 3)
    - Neurology Dept. History and Info (folder 1) 1987 (Box 3)
    - Neurology Dept. Info (folder 2), (dates unknown) (Box 3)
    - Neuro Newscast (dept. newsletter) 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - NIMH Diagnostic Interview Schedule w/Intake Face Sheet 1989 (Box 3)
    - Presidential Initiative Fund (PIF) 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Training Grant Correspondence 1991-1997 (Box 3)
- Decade of the Brain (DoB)
  The Decade of the Brain series (1 box) largely consists of correspondence relating to the project of the same name, including, but not limited to, funding, the AAN Geriatrics Committee, minutes, and Decade of the Brain Steering Committee info. The Decade of the Brain was a project (?) that declared the years 1990-2000 as a time to focus on diseases and disorders of the brain.
  - Advisory Panel on Alzheimer's Disease 1992 (Box 4)
  - Agenda, Minutes, DoB Task Force, DoB Project Update 1991, 1994 (Box 4)
  - American Academy of Neurology (AAN)
    - Committee on Sections 1994-1997, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Geriatric Education 1989-1991, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Geriatric Neurology Section 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Geriatrics Committee (Box 4)
    - Geriatrics Education Subcommittee 1993-1994 (Box 4)
    - Geriatrics Section 1989-1993 (Box 4)
    - Movement Disorders Section 1996 (Box 4)
    - Public Policy Committee 1995 (Box 4)
    - Section on Geriatrics 1996 (Box 4)
  - Animals in Research 1987-1991 (Box 4)
  - Attainable Objectives for 2000, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence 1990-1995, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Decade of the Brain
    - Implementation Plan 1990, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
    - Resolution 1989 (Box 4)
    - Retreat 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Statement 1990 (Box 4)
    - Steering Committee 1990-1991, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Funding/Committee on Sections 1995 (Box 4)
  - Minutes 1992-1995, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - National Advisory Mental Health Council Report to Congress on the Decade of the Brain 1988 (Box 4)
  - National Coalition for Research (empty) (Box 4)
  - National Foundation for Brain Research (NFBR) 1990-1992 (Box 4)
  - Neuroimaging Section Curriculum 1994 (Box 4)
  - Neuroimaging Subspecialty 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - VA Liaison Committee 1991-1992 (Box 4)
- Lectures/Presentations
  The Lectures/Presentations (1 box) series comprises materials from the various national and international lectures, workshops, symposiums, and conferences that Gilman attended. This series also includes Grand Rounds (both correspondence and actual case studies).
  - 1st International Brainstorming Conference on Progressive Supranuclear Palsy (PSP) 1999 (Box 5)
  - 4th International Conference on Alzheimer's Disease 1994 (Box 5)
  - XV International Symposium on Cerebral Blood Flow and Metabolism 1991 (Box 5)
  - XVI World Congress of Neurology 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - AAN Cerebellar Hypotonia 1989 (Box 5)
  - Alzheimer's Disease Markers Meeting 1999 (Box 5)
  - Drug Harmonization in Dementia (London) 1995 (Box 5)
  - Grand Rounds
    - Case Studies 1981, 1983, 1986-1987, 1990-1993, 1999, 2001 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Health Insurance Association America (HIAA)-The Clinical Approach of PET 1991 (Box 5)
  - Imaging in Neurological Rehabilitation 1994 (Box 5)
  - International Symposium on Ataxia (Boston) 1991 (Box 5)
  - Intraspinal Transplantation and Clinical Application: Theoretical "Bench to Bedside" Transition (University of Florida) 1993 (Box 5)
  - Mechanisms for the Recovery of Function After Chronic Injury to the Nervous System workshop 1993 (Box 5)
  - Migraine 1989 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Papers 1986 (Box 5)
  - Molecular Basis of Therapy in Neurology 1997 (contains slides) (Box 5)
  - Multiple System Atrophy (MSA) Meeting 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - Neural Control of Movement Conference 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Neurology for Psychiatrists 1997 (Box 5)
  - Pan American Conference 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - PET Imaging Studies in Progressive Dementia 1987 (Box 5)
  - Sigma-Tau Foundation Lecture (Rome) 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Sleep Disorders 2001, 2003 (Box 5)
  - Srinivasan Lecture (India) 1996-1999 (Box 5)
  - The Cerebellum in Health and Disease (Tubingen, Germany) 1998 (Box 5)
  - The Cerebellum in Motor Control: Current Controversies (Tubingen) 1984, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Vivian L. Smith Lecture (Baylor) 1991-1993 (Box 5)
  - Wartenberg Lecture 1994-1995 (Box 5)
- Denny-Brown Material
  The Denny-Brown series (1 box) is a unique part of this collection in that it does not contain materials directly attributed to Gilman, nor does it focus on the works of Denny-Brown himself, who was a mentor to Gilman. Gilman later served as executor of Denny-Brown's estate. This series provides background on a larger collection of materials related to Denny-Brown that were previously held by the Bentley before being transferred to the National Museum of Medicine in Washington, D.C. The materials included in the Gilman collection consist largely of material about Denny-Brown complied by Gilman and contain video annotations of films done by Denny-Brown, information on the acquisition of Denny-Brown's materials, and miscellaneous correspondence.
  - Denny-Brown Collection Correspondence 1993-1995, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Videotape Annotations 1994 (Box 6)
  - Papers re: Denny-Brown 1996, 1999, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Denny-Brown Gift Fund (cataloging project) 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - Bentley Historical Library (re: Denny-Brown collection) 1981-1988 (Box 6)
  - Denny-Brown Gift Account Info 1984-1986 (Box 6)
  - Denny-Brown Films (folder 1) 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - Denny-Brown Films (folder 2) 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous.
    - 1994, 2003 (Box 6)
    - 1990-1994, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
      (contains photos and negative)
  - Miscellaneous. Correspondence
    - 1991-1994 (Box 6)
    - 1981-1982, 1996-1998 (Box 6)
      (also contains biographies and obituaries)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 6)
- Research
  The Research series (3 boxes) is further divided into two sub-series. The first, Positron Emission Tomography (PET), consists of one box of materials dealing with the history and implementation of PET, program project site visits, grant, budget, and account info, and information regarding the Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center (MADRC). The second sub-series (2 boxes) contains several of Gilman's individual research papers, as well as correspondence related to the publishing of his work. Some papers may have more than one draft. These are the oldest materials in the collection, with dates ranging from 1961 to 1977, although the dates of some materials are unknown. Only a small sample of Gilman's research is included, but the material here is indicative of his methodology and interests.
  - Positron Emission Tomography (PET)
    - Community Outreach Programs 1991-1994, 1998 (Box 7)
    - Data Coordination Meetings 1994-1995 (Box 7)
    - Education Core 1992-1994 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Alzheimer's Disease Research Center (MADRC)
      - Clinical Core 1990-1992, 1994-1995 (Box 7)
      - Consultants 1992 (Box 7)
      - Detroit Satellite 1993-1995 (Box 7)
      - Traverse City Satellite 1992-1995 (Box 7)
    - National Institute on Aging, Alzheimer's Disease Center and Satellite Diagnostic and Treatment Clinics 1994 (Box 7)
    - Neuropathology Core 1993-1996, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - PET Alcohol Project/PET-ADRC (BGR) 1987, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
    - PET Consent Form 1991-1992 (Box 7)
    - Program Project Competing Renewal
      - Account info and summary statement 1984, 1987 (Box 7)
      - Animal use application 1986, 1988-1989, 1991 (Box 7)
      - Budget 1988 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence 1987-1989 (Box 7)
      - Graybiel visit 1987 (Box 7)
    - Grant Budget Info 1985-1986, 1988-1989 (Box 7)
    - History 1978 (Box 7)
    - History 1978
      [RESTRICTED; removed to vault storage]
    - History (folder3)/PET Grant Weekly Meeting 1979 (Box 7)
    - Institutional Review Board (IRB)/RDRC 1988, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Positron Emission Tomography 1978-1979 (Box 7)
    - Program project site visit (Program Project grant) 1984, 1987-1989, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - SDTC 1995 (Box 7)
    - Technology Assessment Committee 1989-1992 (Box 7)
  - Research Papers
    - Neuromuscular Transmission: Lecture undated (Box 8)
    - Pyramidal Tract Function: Lecture undated (Box 8)
    - MS: Alpha Motoneuron Responses in Decerebellate Cats 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    - MS: 4 & 6 Ablation in Monkeys-Final (file 1) 1973 (Box 8)
      (contains filmstrips)
    - MS: Alpha Ablation in Monkeys-Final (file 2) 1970-1972 (Box 8)
    - Dystonia Musculorum Deformans 1969 (Box 8)
    - Familial Dystonia Paraplegic Data 1960-1964, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
      (contains photos and graphs)
    - Author Correspondence 1975-1976 (Box 8)
    - Publishing Correspondence 1974-1977 (Box 8)
    - Alpha Motor Pool Excitability: Manuscript (ANA thesis) 1967-1968 (Box 8)
      (contains images)
    - Alpha Activity After Cerebellectomy, Experimental Protocols 1966-1967, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Dystonia From Cerebral Ablation: Lit. and Final Draft 1965 (Box 8)
    - Input-Output Studies, Decerebellate Monkeys 1968 (Box 8)
    - Thalmic Projections to Cerebral Cortex in Monkeys: Data and Manuscript undated (Box 8)
    - Muscle Receptors: Lecture 1984 (Box 9)
    - Basal Ganglia Lesions on Spindle Activity 1975-1976 (Box 9)
    - Encyclopedia Article 1976-1977 (Box 9)
    - Handbook of Motor Physiology 1976-1977 (Box 9)
    - Cerebellar Disorders 1975 (Box 9)
    - Speech Disorders in Cerebellar Disease 1977 (Box 9)
    - Cerebral Disorder After Open Heart Operation: Records of Neurological Exams 1963-1964 (Box 9)
    - Cerebral Disorders After Open Heart Operation: Pathology 1963 (Box 9)
      (contains slides and photos)
    - Decerebrate Phenomena After Carotid Amytal Injection: Residual Material 1961-1962 (Box 9)
      (contains photos)
    - Chronic Cerebellar Stimulation in the Monkey 1973-1975 (Box 9)
      (contains filmstrips and images)
    - Cerebellar Stimulation in the Monkey: Electron Microscopic and Biochemical Observations 1974, 1976 (Box 9)
      (contains slides and images)
    - Pyramid Section Experiments-Muscle Spindles, Early Version undated (Box 9)
    - Pyramid Section Experiments-Animal With Spindle Recordings 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Muscle Spindle Activity in Dystonic and Spastic Monkeys 1965-1966 (contains illustration and films) (Box 9)
    - ANA Presentation: Pyramidal Tract Section in Monkeys 1969-1970 (Box 9)
      (contains image photocopies)
    - Pyramidotomy Histological Reconstructions 1970 (Box 9)
      (contains filmstrips and illustrations)